Guide to the John and Eleanor Reuling Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
John and Eleanor Reuling Papers
1920-1965
RG 120
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(8 boxes)
Letters, reports, and writings document American mission work in South Africa from 1927 to the 1960s. John A. Reuling was director of teachers' training at Adams College, Natal, South Africa, serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions, from 1927 to 1941. After 1946 he was an administrator for the United Church Board for World Ministries, serving first as regional secretary for Africa and then as general secretary for Mission. Eleanor Swanson Reuling also taught at Adams College and assisted her husband in his work.
Reuling, John A.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
1997 Gift of United Church Board for World Ministries; 2002 Gift of the Reuling family.
Biographical / Historical
Born in Osceola, Nebraska in 1906, John A. Reuling graduated from Michigan State College and received an M.A. from Cornell University. From 1927 to 1941, he was director of teachers' training at Adams College, Natal, South Africa, serving under the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions. He also served as farm manager and vice-principal of Adams College and District Commissioner for the African Boy Scouts.
From 1942 to 1945, Reuling was president of Northland College in Ashland, Wisconsin. He was awarded an honorary degree of Doctor of Laws from Northland College in 1945.
Beginning in 1946, Reuling was Africa Secretary for the American Board and its successor, the United Church of Christ's Board for World Ministries. From 1962 until his retirement in 1971, Reuling was General Secretary for Mission, United Church Board for World Ministries. John Reuling died in 1990.
Eleanor Swanson Reuling was born in 1903 and graduated from Michigan State College. She married John Reuling in 1926, and was appointed as an ABCFM missionary to South Africa in 1927. In addition to raising the couple's four children and providing hospitality for many visitors, Eleanor also taught at Adams College as needed and tutored students who had special needs. Following their return to the U.S. Eleanor continued her work of hospitality, was active in volunteer work, including on the board of Church Women United in New Jersey, and filled various educational and administrative posts for the United Church Board for World Ministries on an interim basis. She was also an accomplished writer. She edited newsletters and prepared interpretive material for the cause with which she was involved, as well as writing a biography of James C. Bryant entitled First Saint to the Zulus. Eleanor Reuling died in 1983.
Scope and Contents
An initial donation of material processed in 1997 has been augmented by additional papers received from the Reuling family in 2002. This collection provides valuable documentation of American Protestant mission work in Africa during the period when the Reulings were working there (1927-1942) and thereafter through the 1960s in connection with John Reuling's work as regional secretary for Africa for the American Board.
Regular and detailed letters written to family members in the U.S. from 1927 to 1941 provide information about the mission work in South Africa and the life of a missionary family. This correspondence is complemented by writings and collected material related to the Reulings' work in Africa. An abridged and edited collection of the letters of John and Eleanor Reuling 1927-1941 has been compiled and edited by their daughter Edna Reuling Wade: Praise Names of Reuling: a Zulu Song (2015).
Several books were received with the collection. Copies of the books already held by the Divinity LIbrary has been retained with the Reuling Papers while others have been added to the library's cataloged collection.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1927-1964, n.d.
II. Collected Material, 1920s-1963
III. Writings, 1960-1965, n.d.
IV. Biographical Documentation, 1926-1990,n.d.
Missions -- South Africa; Missionaries; Reuling, Eleanor S.; Reuling, John A.; American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions; United Church Board for World Ministries
- Correspondence, Series I
  Related Materials
  An abridged and edited collection of the letters of John and Eleanor Reuling 1927-1941 has been compiled and edited by their daughter Edna Reuling Wade: Praise Names of Reuling: a Zulu Song (2015).
  - Material received in 1997
    - Personal and office correspondence of JAR, 1942-1958, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1-8)
    - Circular letters of JAR, from Angola, South Africa, Southern Rhodesia, 1946-1960 (Box 1, Folder 9-16)
    - Letter with description of granting of Nobel Peace Prize toChief Albert Luthuli, a close friend of JAR, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Circular letters from missionaries (mostly ABCFM) in Angola, 1948-1959 (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
    - Circular letters from missionaries in South Africa, 1949-1961 (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
    - Circular letters from missionaries in Southern Rhodesia, 1952-1964, n.d (Box 2, Folder 23-25)
    - Circular letters from missionaries in other countries, 1953-1957, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Material received in 2002
    - Letters from Reulings to family in U.S.
      - Letters to family, 1927 Jun-Dec (Box 3, Folder 37-43)
      - Photocopies of 1927 letters, 1927 Jun-Dec (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Letters to family, 1928 Jan-Dec (Box 3, Folder 45-51)
      - Photocopies of 1928 letters, 1928 Jan-Dec (Box 4, Folder 52-53)
      - Letters to family, 1929 Jan-Dec (Box 4, Folder 54-59)
      - Photocopies of 1929 letters, 1929 Jan-Dec (Box 4, Folder 60-61)
      - Letters to family, 1930 Jan-Dec (Box 4, Folder 62-67)
      - Photocopies of 1930 letters, 1930 Jan-Dec (Box 5, Folder 68-69)
      - Letters to family, 1931 Jan-Dec (Box 5, Folder 70-73)
      - Photocopies of 1931 letters, 1931 Jan-Dec (Box 5, Folder 74-75)
      - Letters to family, 1932 Jan-Dec (Box 5, Folder 76-78)
      - Photocopies of 1932 letters, 1932 Jan-Dec (Box 5, Folder 79-80)
      - Letters to family, 1933 Jan-Nov (Box 5, Folder 81-83)
      - Photocopies of 1933 letters, 1933 Jan-Nov (Box 5, Folder 84)
      - Letters to family, 1934 Mar-Dec (Box 6, Folder 85-87)
      - Photocopies of 1934 letters, 1934 Mar-Dec (Box 6, Folder 88)
      - Letters to family, 1935 Jan-Dec (Box 6, Folder 89-91)
      - Photocopies of 1935 letters, 1935 Jan-Dec (Box 6, Folder 92-93)
      - Letters to family, 1936 Jan-Dec (Box 6, Folder 94-96)
      - Photocopies of 1936 letters, 1936 Jan-Dec (Box 6, Folder 97-98)
      - Letters to family, 1937 Jan-Dec (Box 6, Folder 99-101)
      - Photocopies of 1937 letters, 1937 Jan-Dec (Box 6, Folder 102-103)
      - Letters to family, 1938 Jan-Dec (Box 7, Folder 104-105)
      - Photocopies of 1938 letters, 1938 Jan-Dec (Box 7, Folder 106-107)
      - Letters to family, 1939 Jan-Dec (Box 7, Folder 108-110)
      - Photocopies of 1939 letters, 1939 Jan-Dec (Box 7, Folder 111-112)
      - Letters to family, 1940 Jan-Nov (Box 7, Folder 113-115)
      - Photocopies of 1940 letters, 1940 Jan-Nov (Box 7, Folder 116-117)
      - Letters to family, 1941 Jan-Dec (Box 7, Folder 118)
      - Photocopies of 1941 letters, 1941 Jan-Dec (Box 7, Folder 119)
    - Correspondence of others
      - Other family members (siblings), 1939-1940 (Box 7, Folder 120)
      - Miscellaneous acquaintances/colleagues (Box 7, Folder 121)
      - Fragments and notes, 1928-1940 (Box 7, Folder 122)
- Collected Material, Series II
  - Material received in 1997
    - Regarding mission work in Angola
      - Reports of John T. Tucker, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Proposed 5-year plan for union institutions, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Report of secretary of Angola Evangelical Alliance, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Minutes of meeting of mission bodies, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Regarding mission work in South Africa
      - Report of South African Mission, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Memorandum to Minister of Native Affairs, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Adams College reports, minutes, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - American Board semi-annual meeting, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Comments by JAR on S. Africa Mission, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Memo to JAR from Inanda Community (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Regarding mission work in Southern Rhodesia
      - Comments by JAR on medical work, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Minutes of Missions Council, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Other
      - Conference on Christian Education in Changing Africa, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Material received 2002
    - Personal items: related to Scouting (JAR)
      - Personal items: related to Scouting (JAR), 1920s (Box 8, Folder 126)
      - Personal items (JAR) (Box 8, Folder 127)
      - Related to South Africa mission - programs, celebrations (Box 8, Folder 128)
      - Newsclippings - local interest, South Africa (Box 8, Folder 129)
      - Newsclippings - re. war stories (Box 8, Folder 130)
      - Newsclippings - re. politics and missions, 1957-1961 (Box 8, Folder 131)
      - Eleanor Reuling's "Inanda" photo scrapbook (Box OV-1)
      - Books: The Story of the American Board (1910), The Zulu-Kafir Language, (1899), Zulu-Kafir Dictionary 1857), Recent Developments in the South African Mission Field (1958); Additional books were added to YDSL collection: Textbook fo Zulu Grammar (1931), Letters of the American Missionaries 1835-1838 (1950), Zulu English Dictionary (1948). (Box OV-1)
- Writings, Series III
  - Material received 1997
    - Writings of John A. Reuling
      - "The Mission and Governments", 1965 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - African greetings, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Writings of Eleanor Reuling
      - Notes, writings re. African missions and African women, incl. wife of Chief Albert Luthuli (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Material received 2002
    - Writings of Eleanor Reuling
      - "Memories of Africa", n.d. (Box 7, Folder 123)
      - "First Saint to the Zulus" (biography of James C. Bryant), 1960 (Box 7, Folder 124)
- Biographical Information, Series IV
  - Material received 1997
    - Biographical information (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Material received 2002
    - Re. marriage, family, ABCFM appointments (Box 8, Folder 132)
    - Obituaries, eulogies, interment and family reunion (Box 8, Folder 133)